hello look buddy welcome back thanks for
joining again I'm really stoked to be
releasing this video with Corey Anton
I'll take a moment and go through his
bio and a little bit about who he is set
context versus some housekeeping so as
I've been announcing since the corona
virus
we have moved by company the circle
Institute has moved all of their
offerings online we are also starting a
part of circling a year-long program
that will be online as well so
information about all of that below we
have opened we have open to the public
events every week and you can get
information on the face book which is
down below and the website and if you're
interested in working with me one on one
please email me my emails below as well
all right so I'm really excited to have
this talk with Corey and I think it'll
be the one of many in the future
hopefully I first was introduced to him
on YouTube years ago like like back
before YouTube is owned by Google I
think where you were they only had like
10 minutes slots that people could load
videos inside of and Corey was one of
the first people that I ever saw that
that actually used used YouTube and a
way to talk about ideas and in a way
that that we're doing right now Corey
was ready that at the beginning of all
that and he's quite accomplished I'm
gonna go ahead and read his bio Corey
anton is a professor of communication
studies at Grand Valley State University
and author of dozens of scholarly papers
and and book chapters his research spans
the fields of existential phenomenology
media ecology
semiotics community ecology the
philosophy of communication and
multidisciplinary communication theory
he's a two-time winner of the media
ecology associations Erving Goffman
award Anton Anton has received a best
author award in 2011 presented by the
philosophy of Communications Division of
the National Communication associated
Association Anton has also won numerous
teaching awards including GBS use few
teaching excellence award and the
Graduate Student Association outstanding
faculty member award
past president of media ecology
Association past chair of semiotic s--
and communication division of the
National Communication Association and
past editor of the journal exploration
and media ecology anton is a fellow of
the International communication
Institute and he currently serves as
vice president of the Institute of
semantics of general semantics so as you
can see he's very well educated he
teaches a lot and he's his is the range
of his interests span multiple fields
and the thing that has that my
connection with him has really been his
his work with existential phenomenology
and it's specifically his real and depth
interest in understanding and
communication and and specifically media
and how phenomenology and media ecology
you know obviously in the in the age of
the Internet is more pertinent that we
think I think we can even understand so
we talked a lot about that some real
interesting things about reading real
interesting things about just I mean we
go really deep I think really appreciate
him as a thinker and he's from from
listening to him in his videos on his
YouTube channels all these years have
have opened up a lot of horizons for me
more than I think I can even totally
understand that's the nature of horizons
all right enjoy
it's its own ecosystem right there's a
there's a the thing that I the thing
I've been appreciating about these about
these conversations and what I'm what
I'm seeing is that they're spurring on
other conversations that are being
viewed right and there's there's a way
in which you can see this you know each
different conversations are being
pregnant by other ones so you really get
this sense of a something something
living or something being created and by
a lot of different people like for
example there's you know you know
there's there's Paul van der clay who's
a minister right who's basically kind of
taking on like really exploring all of
these kind of secular ideas right while
from the perspective of being a minister
and really grappling with them right and
having conversations and it's kind of
interesting because you know if we look
at like my understanding of Heidegger's
notion about like technology is this
kind of techno and framing right you
know Quranic figure out like get rid of
all the background and only like look at
the ground and
this happens to be and I think what you
guys are doing back in the day on on
YouTube and what we're doing here is I
wonder if this is one of the places and
I'm I'm curious to hear what you think
about this um where technology is
actually affording write something
untechnical to come in right so like I
don't know anything less technological
than a meandering right conversation
that goes on for a long time
right and it's interesting because well
one thing is that they're finding that
people actually have an attention span
that they that they didn't know that
they had when it was just the network's
right so it's like the network's just
thought we were all kind of stupid okay
like you just got these these little
sound bites of things you know because
they were different constraint as well
but you know you have people like Joe
Rogan and you know that are doing these
three-hour long meandering pretty deep
you know it'll actually vast kinds of
conversations and people are actually
tuning in sure well I think what I said
what all this okay I think
yeah so with podcast sort of stuff where
it's it's available for people and
people have longer commute commutes and
they're doing it as a multitasking and
they may not only could they be doing
different things while it's on in the
background and there's that going on I
think you're right I mean there is some
sense of which all of this though is
elevating the overall expectations for
kind of engagement but I think as far as
the height of your stuff you know I I
guess my own sensibility would be that
no I it there really is something very
insidious about the way that things are
being framed and the way I would say is
that the technologies in frame by way of
an eight historicism that if you take
something like let's take psychology
just as an example you know I think
traditionally anyway you know psychology
was something like an experimental and
it's a body of knowledge but it was it
was built upon being familiar with
certain thinkers and certain traditions
and you might say well you know in the
psychoanalytic tradition we're gonna
begin with Freud and we're gonna try to
look at how young reacted to Freud and
then we try to understand Lacan wears
now I think people say we don't have
time for all that you point to something
in the brain and unless you can point to
something in the brain this is all a
bunch of malarkey so I think there's a
kind of rampant a historicism that the
technologies are introducing partly
because it's information overload but I
mean I think look at people like Richard
lambs work and people who've done work
on economics of attention there was a
time when what was short or what was
what was sparse or you know in need was
information and we had more than enough
attention and we didn't know how to you
know to get the information that we
needed
where's now there's an absolute overflow
of information more than one could ever
consume and was scarce is attention so
the information is now in abundance the
attention is scarce and because of that
you know those those two things coming
together have you know they really
unleashed a kind of rampant a
historicism and there's other factors as
well as it has to do with diaspora and
the culture has to do with you know
changing ways
people are no longer in extended
families which is parents raising their
kids rather than grandparents mean I
think that slows down some of the
cultural change as well
but yeah I think I think there it really
is an important issue that you know stem
is coming back with a vengeance
and I think philosophers are
increasingly gonna be and I think that
you need to invoke Jordan Peterson is
such a great example where you know
people aren't really interested in
philosophical ideas as much as they are
in empirical based psychology I mean
that's what he Jordan Peterson brings a
lot of empirical based psychology to
bear on his claims everything from you
know evolutionary biology but the
psychology it's grounded in a lot of
empirical studies and so I think classic
philosophical ideas are giving way to
technocratic thought empirically driven
kind of scientific thought and maybe
that's a good thing
I mean maybe really you know important
for people to be a lot more attuned to a
scientific worldview but that's how it's
I mean I think for heidegger's taste
this would have been a killing of
philosophy and poetry yeah
philosophy and poetry and the offing
right now oh yeah totally Oh totally
well that's that that's the one I think
one of the things that I'm you know when
I to ever to whatever degree I'm part of
this right
the the thing I'm trying to see that I
think I'm Avoca
or attempting to evoke is that that
sense of how you call it like that that
sense of the way because right now I'm
doing a series where I'm with with
another like a another philosopher um
we're going through and reading the
Platonic dialogues straight through
right and like and then commenting on
them and you know riffing on them and
bringing different people in and there's
that sense of where I feel there
personally indebted um to and I've heard
you talk about this as well of like what
it is to really grapple with a text
right and with an author in in that in
this strange sense where I noticed that
for me cuz I don't have it I don't have
an academic background um I went to art
school you know shortly after high
school and but I got something spoke to
me and with Heidegger and I used to you
know as a poor student so but I used to
live across the street from Barnes and
Noble so no one read the Heidegger book
so I'd go you know I basically had my
own collection and I go there and I
would just like get amped up on coffee
and start reading Heidegger and I'd no
idea what that sign was for like I don't
know the first three chapters or
something but there was this this this
sense this sense that something grabs
your interest like from some horizon
opens up and what's mysterious to me is
how do I know to be interested by
something which I find out years later
right as this whole world that opened up
but something captures me but it's not
it's not something I know like I can
explain and I think this is some of the
danger that you're talking about with
like the hyper scientism right that
comes up where it's all the actual right
we don't even notice that they're there
they're imposing a metaphysics on that
right right in in a lot of ways but but
then reap from just grappling by myself
like trying to figure out what what I'm
actually reading
was fascinating to me was at the same
time I started reading Heidegger is when
I started this practice called circling
with a group of my friends in San
Francisco and I would like read I dagur
and then I go in circle on the beach
right we just get around and we just get
like we just go into what was in the
present moment right and we end up in
all kinds of places which ended up
becoming something like a practice
that's actually like spread throughout
the world which is fascinating too to
find myself inside of that but but it
wasn't until about three years later and
I didn't know what the connection was
between what I was reading and what I
was doing and then three years later all
of a sudden I just kind of opened my
eyes and I looked around and I started
to catch the the UM like the grammatical
structures of the way people talked
right and there were things like
backgrounds and foregrounds and worlds
and getting someone's world and horizons
and opened up and and I was like oh whoa
that it gave me a sense of that I had no
idea that that was bleeding over that
that there was something about reading a
text right and I would imagine this is
the way with any any kind of like text
that's just beyond your ability to make
sense of it but there's something
speaking to you and so you read it like
I would try to grasp Heidegger and I
would like have to step so far outside
of my my frame of reference to kind of
look back to try to attempt to
understand that and I do that over and
over and over again and what I didn't
realize that was happening was it it
transformed how I saw how I listened
right on some level that I didn't and
that's that that sense of having a
breeding practice or we're Appling with
things that are just um outside of our
own this is a good example to me it's
partly why I like you know I have the
luxury so I mean I realized that it's
not everyone has
you know I have University Professors so
I get to work with young people I get to
be in the classroom has probably been
why I've been less inclined to spend
time on YouTube currently because I do
have other things to do with my time and
I and I prefer the face-to-face with
students and I really do prefer the
texts for some of those reasons you're
saying you know they won't so young
people you know think anybody right when
you're when you're really young you just
run around and you play you chase things
and you're in the woods who's got stuff
and you have no idea what's gonna happen
when puberty sets and all suddenly you
start finding different things
interesting and you start changing your
orientations and there's sort of
newfound capacities in your body all
this kind of stuff and I think something
similar happens to a lot of people
around the age of 20 where or in their
mid-20s they they don't see it coming
but suddenly they go you know what I
think I might be an intellectual and
they face through a certain engagement
with particular authors particular texts
sort of opening the history and they say
wow you know I actually enjoy thinking I
enjoy these kind of exercise of my mind
of trying to figure out what an author
means and the kind of distance that that
gives me to come back to myself and so
yeah I mean I think there's there's
something so about that and I guess I'll
just wanna real quickly sort of riff on
that which is you know when people are
listening to us if anyone would actually
be listening to us right now
you know they in listening they're kind
of allowing us to think their thoughts
for them that is to really listen is to
open to the other and let their words
kind of do the thinking now they can be
objecting or agreeing or disagreeing and
doing other sort of I guess dynamic
relations of their own thought to it but
it's very different than reading when I
sit down to read the only way for the
author to gain a voice is for me to give
the author the voice that is I have to
engage in speech production in order for
that author to be heard at all so
there's an exercise and a growth in
articulate see like one
to grow articulate in one's own speech
production in order to accurately
pronounce and to give voice to
particular text so I think there is a
very real disadvantage as people just
listen to podcasts and as they plug in
they may be gaining information but they
may not be exercising the kind of speech
production skills that come along just
inherently with becoming a reader
interesting I've never quite made that
connection or that in that next step
because I've I have noticed and I and I
think listening I think listening is
perhaps the the last the most
determinant phenomena right of being
human that gets very little air time
that's why it's so interesting is like
why are we able to listen to some people
at certain points and hear what they
have to say and other points we could
try as much and to hear what they say
but we just weren't able to hear it it
is a fascinating listening you know is a
skill it's a competency but there's also
there's something like there's blockers
or developmental you know things where
you get the Charlie Brown effect where
the teachers talking you hear why it is
you're listening it just it's not there
you know so there is something about it
I think you can see it in political
discourse you know as people are
listening they hear selectively and it
takes great great effort and real
concerted attention to try to not just
filter it into a tunnel and or a silo
that's self confirming for their
ideologies in their yeah the vulnerable
ego needs to defend itself yeah that in
that I think that would you I mean would
you say that that sense of the
vulnerable ego we need to defend
themselves is
is probably one of the ways that we
don't listen
exactly right cuz you're right because
I've noticed that sense to you of where
and I want to go I want to go back to
this thing he said about the about
reading a text right as is like having
to produce speech in some way is yours
but it's not yours so it's really I get
this kind of kinesthetic sense about it
as you're talking about it really Oh
Ponty I mean really Ponte I basically
become the other as I read them because
you know I'm sort of wearing the other
and I'm I'm walking around in their
symbolic universe and then it's becoming
as I become myself through the other
yeah huh it's so interesting because I
would imagine there's that sense of
becoming another is is is you know it's
definitely it seems to be different when
I when I myself and I put myself in your
position and I walk around that's not
really being you it's like when it's
when I
ib q pi your position so thoroughly that
i begin to have the the background that
you have that allows me to see it
differently as you would see it
differently on some level right that
absence is starts to get at levels of
like identity and but that i think i
think and i think what i'm what's on the
horizon is we're talking is just that
sense of a certain indebtedness i have
to that practice of yeah I mean I think
figure-ground is a great way to come at
it yeah when you're first starting the
author is a figure in your the ground
and that's the difficulty of
assimilation is that you're bringing
your own ground but that's you
assimilate basically you're not turning
it into something that you you're
turning yourself into something that can
match it this is what we call the law
requisite variety you know that a system
can only handle the complexity of the
system that it would adapt to by being
is complicated or is internally
complexified so I am encountering a text
I learned to internally complexify
myself to be able to meet it by the time
I'm able to do that it's become ground
for me and now I look with the author as
a lens rather than me looking at the
text man that's pretty that's really
quite neat that's quite deep and
it just I think I'm getting the sense of
I think what Rebecca would call
participatory knowing right of that of
that sense and way you know in the way
to get at this that I've heard expert or
knowing the way that he talks about it
it's is it David Bentley Hart the the
the the modern he's like a continental
theologian and he's really taking on
like the the New Atheists he's really
funny and in in air getting pompous in
this kind of cool way but he talks about
you know he so he writes these books and
he's kind of arguing with with like you
know the New Atheists and he in he's
he's responding to the claim that
something about like that arguing about
whether or not Dawkins can test for
whether or not there's a God right and
he's like well okay so here's what
Dawkins would have to do is he'd have to
he'd have to just probably spend you
know well you have to go through all the
rituals right for months and he'd pray
and the ceremonies and the rites of
everything that comes with the Christian
rules and fully participate in it for a
couple of years and then we can start to
get at that question there's that sense
where part like in a certain way that
you can't kind of in that I think what
he's talking about is that it's when
it's that full figure-ground immersion
right an enactment of both what's
foreground but what goes background in
order for you to an act with the
foreground that actually brings
something like presence right the sense
of being something like living and
present I'm just getting that sense as
you're talking about like as we're
talking about reading in some way it's a
it's a deeper level of like it's not
just abstract about being informed but
you're actually like walking in to
another's world and finding yourself
with a background
that then you can converse with the
author right I remember when I had my
colleague here Robert Mayberry when he
was still alive
and I was in his office and we we would
regularly meet and talk about books and
get readings together and one day I was
in his office I looked at him I said
Robert what exactly would your mind have
been like it you're not learn to read
and he just laughed out loud and we both
just sat there and went it doesn't make
any sense I mean the the borders between
brains maybe something that's visible
but the borders between minds is not
minds are much more of a
socio-historical dynamic and they have a
lot to do with literacy and that you
know we've become the particular kinds
of minds that we have through all kinds
of technological mediations clocks
calendars but the literate word I mean
that the written word the printed word
has shaped our consciousness and opened
us to history in ways that would we
would be in like a mythical time rather
than a historical time and they look at
like something like Foster's work no
villain Flusser using a lot of really
interesting stuff on sort of the the
mythical and then the rise of the
historic and how right now historical
consciousness is slowly going to be
displaced by a new kind of myth and it's
the image culture you know I mean image
culture I mean this is you know it's
also I you know Lance Strait has some
really good stuff on this where you know
I think if there's a concern it's that
the articulate word the thoughtful word
is sort of being attacked on two sides
on one side it's the image and on other
side it's the number and so hyper
quantitative rationality with everything
being reducible to something that can be
quantified and reason about in terms of
a mathematical model or it's something
that you just apprehend through an image
but the spoken word the articulate word
is neither of those and you know there's
a depth to the spoken word that yeah
it's not to deny that we can make
representations by taking the spoken
word and calling it the letters on the
page and it's not to deny that we can
run
kinds of numbers about you know
statistical normalities and linguistics
and other kinds of things but it's to
say isn't there something that's missing
let me try to reduce it down to image
and number I think there is yeah oh yeah
yeah it's like it's it's kind of trying
to it's trying to read the text through
like measuring the shape of the letter
or something right yeah exactly
exactly you know and it's I I think you
know what one can embrace and talk about
the importance of I spend you know the
importance of you know I think some
people they need more statistical
literacy people need basic competencies
in math they need basic competencies in
statistical and scientific methodologies
but that said I am you know I I lament
the loss of the humanities and I think
there we could talk about the way that
this is opening humanity is to larger
platforms it's bringing outside of the
Academy and I think that's true I think
you know be very easily to oversimplify
all of this I think it is very
complicated and a lot of different
levels so it's probably more of
everything in some way probably more
poetry more history books more
philosophy books than ever before have
been written like right now they're
coming off the shelf so I mean some of
this all you guys on how going to cast
the narrative but I think the sort of
slow steady deep appreciation for
historical thought steeping in the
tradition I see that as on the decline
people just don't have time for that and
we live in a world where it's the
electric media have now they interlocked
us in such a way that the rate in the
pace of life is radically different than
it was just like 20 25 years ago when I
was in graduate school it just didn't
seem like like right now you know we
were talking you know that this
coronavirus were all on lockdown and the
universities I mean it's almost as if
they're expecting us not really but it's
almost as if they're expecting us within
two days to go from all you know
face-to-face instruction seamlessly to
an online mode of delivery you want to
go a crisis and a pandemic is happening
why don't we take a week off and just
think about other things like there's
never gonna be another snow
you know it used to be when I went to
school on the day one the professor
would show up and they would hand out
the syllabus and you would learn about
the class and you would go get the
readings after the class now they opened
the blackboard site before the class
even begins there's homework assigned
for that first day everything is moving
at an interlocking ringing pace looking
in the coronavirus how possibly when
this is spread across the globe before
mass air travel yeah what thinking years
yeah Oh totally I mean it's the airplane
and the logic of rapid you know biblical
you know have a business meeting in New
York and let's make it back to the end
of the day you know you're gonna jet out
there in the morning and jet back at
night people you know I think that many
people they're stressed they're anxiety
ridden they don't know how to live at
this inhuman pace they're over schedule
yeah that information overload again
that leads itself to a kind of a
historicism and it leads itself to a
technocratic orientation of learning and
knowledge itself it's sort of like what
do I do with the knowledge like knowing
and be knowledgeable
that sounds antiquated we're gonna
recite some poems by her acquaint
whereas I think now we say well what do
you do with that yeah yeah in fact let's
see I would say it seems increasingly
basically what I'm hearing you say is
like our sense of temporality is like
just in the last 25 years is we're
looking at a very different
temporalities yes and part of it is
funny like I I mean I'm starting to have
thoughts for the first time of like oh
this is what my parents used to say when
they talked about like there's no way
that you can appreciate what you have is
is you're young great I remember going
like I wonder if I can or not right like
it I I'm starting to have some of those
thoughts of like oh this is what they
meant there right there would be no way
to be older when you're younger like
older is a very full embodied thing but
but the sense of what you're talking
about just in like 25 years right within
our generation a radical change in what
shows up as significant and real in such
a drastic way which it ain't like that
used to take hundreds of years right for
it to happen
I mean some way really began with the
Telegraph The Telegraph
made possible a separation of
information and transportation it
created the time zones and it
accelerated the ability to exchange
information created the futures market
in the stock market I mean there's just
a whole bunch of ways that since at
least the 1850s we've been living at a
greater distance from people who lived
historically and now as you say lent the
last 25 with the digital age as more and
more people are living online they don't
have time for commutes they don't have
time for things that involve slow
steeping instead there's just demand for
instantaneous and I think that's
probably the appeal of podcast I mean
the podcast is wonderful you can do
other things while you're listening
mm-hmm right right now I'm wondering I'm
wondering right because this is what
I've been a lot of what I've been just
diving into is is just is I mean I just
think Heidegger was so prophetic in this
regard
right about the whole thing about a the
age of technology and the concealing of
concealment
right the withdrawal of withdrawing in
that sense of my understanding is that
like the deep humanities and kind of
sitting with something and grappling
with it and incubating it and being with
things that you don't know that aren't
immediately useful or intelligible is
all about like it's all about in a
certain sense being aware that
something's concealed right and but yet
that being that glowing as almost
virtuous to move towards and that eats
in order to know that I must become
someone who could write in drawing on
that sense of development and character
that comes through time and call
elevation in challenge and grappling
with things and dead ends and it seems
to me that like when you talked about
you to use this phrase like living
online I'm I really got that sense of
like you're not just talking about being
on the computer on the internet there's
a way in which this structure of the
internet fashions the way that we drive
down the road and what we choose to do
and how we even think our schedule and
right there's a kind of like the online
is now kind of on some sense is
synonymous with the world yeah and I
mean I think would you take things like
relationships you know what what are
they what's the impact of people swiping
right or swipe me and left in their
determining other picking a relationship
partner you know I think the difference
between asking how good am I gonna be in
growing my own skills as a relationship
partner how much are my competencies
what is gonna make or break this is very
different than how do I pick a good one
out there and and I want to sort of like
exactly if we had more information and
we have greater ease all of our
relationship problems would go away and
there is something about compatibility
there is something about having a good
match
don't want to be ignorant there but you
can have a really good match if you
don't know how to make the relationship
work if it's your only confidence the
best partner or they gonna help yeah I
think some people you're under
estimating how it's about their own
growth and instead we want to track them
on a secret or better we think we're
done we're fine everyone else you know
all we need is more information or some
some accessible trick or some against or
secret right right and I said so that
it's when it's slow that that want that
part down it is kind of like zero in on
a bit because this is because part of
the thing that like Heidegger to go back
to category what he talked about is that
the strange things about being in such
like as you would say a truly dark time
is not one in which people are talking
about how dark it is right a truly dark
time is its conceals it's it's dark it's
dark that it's dark
it's darkened park right so it's one of
the ways that I noticed myself in in
trying to figure out I don't know if
it's figure out but like trying to feel
into what is the best way to respond to
this time that to me isn't totally
obvious but I think the hint I've gotten
from Heidegger is when he talked about
like in the saving in in the danger as
the saving power right and in in that
part that that part of responding has to
do with staying awake I think to the
withdrawal of sense or as he would say
it like the withdrawal of being right
the being discloses itself now in its
not being there and and that that kind
of continually noticing the utter
uncanny --mess of this time like so you
so for example like if you really kind
of look it's it's what's so strange is
how strew how how not strange things
occur to people but when you step back
you're like for the for example the
dating thing that you just you just
brought up in my lifetime right and this
is a huge deal it's kind of like how
people couple we've been doing that for
like ever
right it's been like probably the most
central thing that human beings have
done and in a matter of about I would
say I noticed this change happen
probably within two to three years when
I was born and I think we're the last
generation like they have a memory
before the internet right oh yeah I mean
my fifties I remember when TV you know
yeah
totally it's like um I just kind of
lived my life and there was a a a non
conceptual sense that what would happen
is that you go out and you live your
life and somewhere in living your life
you meet somebody and most likely you'll
get married and then you'll have kids
but it's all part of the enacting and
living of your life and that I think was
probably that that version in some
form for I don't know thousands of years
or something like that right to various
degrees to within two years you now
there's a whole separate category called
like finding your partner going to an
app yeah this selectivity proc process
where it's it's actually kind of
situated in this its own category and
all the stuff about compatibility where
you show up into a relationship already
inside of that context of evaluating in
that that that's within a few years that
became the way that you date people
don't actually have a sense of who you
partner with is just an out springing of
your life it's now this thing that you
do and and one of the things I liked on
a you said a lot of really good things
about this that have just really opened
up and I just by the way I just want to
thank you for your videos like yeah I
mean they really have served for me
like they served for me is opening up
vistas and horizons that like I didn't
quite it's like wiggled something free
and then just my attention started
moving towards it and then that horizon
is just yielded so many things that have
really like had an impact on how I see
and understand in you know being in the
world I just really want to thank you
for that I mean you know I'm if you want
you know we can do interview or an
interaction again to a dialogue you know
if you want to chat more that's no
problem
yeah there's just so much that's going
on in all this you know I think that
George ritenour has a book called the
mcdonaldization of society we second its
fifth edition some like that but it's
really good I think if someone we live
in a fast food consumer orientation and
you know I think it's it's a dirty
little truth that people don't want to
admit that not everything can be bought
you know I think capitalism wants to
give it so that it wants to foster the
impression that everything has a price
everything can be bought but you're not
going to be able to buy an understanding
of ID or you're not gonna be able to buy
a good relationship with a partner you
know there are certain things where it's
gonna be you know taking seriously one's
own growth one's own self discipline
weasel of learning how to open to others
and to see that as a task you know I
mean I guess you know this is part that
you were saying just earlier about you
know how we go about mate selection you
know I think it's some way it helps to
look at other countries you know
historically I mean women were basically
they kind of given away for you know
property agreements and arrangements
there really wasn't very much option and
then like arranged marriages are really
interesting sort of model and because I
think in arranged marriages sometimes
sometimes people go well you know I hope
they picked a good partner for me but
they learn how to make things work and
they see the obligation is how to be a
good partner which is very different
than when you're doing
is romantic person-to-person I'm gonna
go fall in love with whoever I want I
mean many traditional societies that
would be punishable by death yeah you
fall in love with someone as rude
you know there's obligations to family
into the larger community so I mean in
some way we've created a society with
lot of liberties but it's I think it's
very you know some way socially
irresponsible I think you look at what's
happening with this coronavirus I think
you're seeing right now the very
beginning of some deep seeds of
socialism being sown in because there
are some people walking around going hey
look I'm young I'm healthy I'm fine
what's the problem of people going well
that's fine but you're putting
vulnerable pop you know parts of the
population at risk and just a little bit
of change of your behavior just a little
bit could really make the difference
between this being an absolute
catastrophe with the hospitals being
overfilled and something that's a little
less you know damaging but I think you
know there are I think younger people
they're more aware I think they're kind
of like well you know I think we should
be more concerned about what's happening
there for other people you know yeah
yeah totally well this is what's it you
know is funny it's yeah you just brought
me back to that sense of you're right
romantic love was like an invention of
them so that the sense of just that what
you're attracted to is innately gonna be
the good thing to do it's usually I mean
psychologists like usually the person
you're attracted to is the person that
like like is the place the person that
won't love you in just the way that your
parents didn't love you so that you can
then feel familiar and then try to
finally get them that sense of arranged
marriage is is really it's really
interesting because now that I'm married
and I'm in my second marriage and it's
real of the Sun and somehow I'm actually
starting to really really get it this
time like I'm like well I was married
once very young for a very short time
and I've been with my wife now for like
20 years and yeah it's it's a the world
of different
between you know what I would call like
someone who is you know best friend and
you you wanted someone who's very
companionate best friend and you start
to think in terms of how do you be a
really great friend and a really good
partner to someone and you be honest
with yourself about whether or not
you're being selfish or you're not
listening and all-sky stuff there's so
much more helpful then you know I'm
gonna try to pick someone who you think
is gonna you know make you look good or
whatever you know what I mean you yeah I
think people get married for the
strangest of reasons well that by
experience of it and it's funny because
I feel like I mean I'm alike you know I
I'm I'm definitely born of the you know
secular humanist through and through
right like of that culture so like any
social norms like I was just kind of
automatically suspect of but I've
actually kind of through being married
it's really interesting I when I went
into it I was just like well you know
it's a formality let's see you do it for
your parents or something like that you
know but actually I feel very wedded and
and interesting is I'm starting to feel
that sense of like you know that's
something's normative in the culture
then it's right you're in a hospital and
you really want to get some care for
your partner just say my partner or my
boyfriend or my girlfriend that doesn't
do much when you say with my wife you
say my husband people respond yeah yes
wool this is a legal thing here that you
know this is a person who's gonna have
some legal action you know would you say
I just a friend some pretend like we
don't recognize that that's really not
institution recognized right well what's
that what's wild is that that sense of
oh whoa there's this almost like this
third entity called the marriage and
oftentimes Breanna and I my wife will
we'll be talking and we'll get through
something that we're used to like years
ago would like it into an argument about
and we'll get done in my awful state you
know I think our relationship is more
mature than us now the sense of of a
respect for a structure that like is
actually giving us right man you know I
teach interpersonal and you know I try
to convey to students that you know
there's you and your partner and then
there's the relationship that you have
and that relationship it does have a
dynamic beyond either of your wills or
your intention and you can do damage to
the relationship and even though both of
you can try to get over it the
relationship has been damaged yeah that
sense of literally being inside of
something right yes yeah you're right it
has a third against quality to it they
kind of give the two papers really I
think that's really true for us to trust
and respect are so crucial if you don't
have trust you don't have respect I
think the other thing is a second to go
about this in framing stuff so this was
about three or four weeks ago I was in a
philosophy colloquium on a Sunday it was
a psychologist a philosopher and I was
from the comm theory area and we're all
talking about artificial intelligence
and the question of you know is it
desirable and how possible it is in
tosca stuff and in the flyer it had the
expression you know faster smarter
sexier younger and maybe immortal you
know so you know questions about AI and
what will it cost um and we had quite a
lovely discussion but I think what came
out of it is we sort of asked what about
wisdom in the information age like if we
would have thrown wiser into that would
it have worked or what do they just pop
right out of the frame yeah you know it
seems as if if we're gonna say quicker
and faster and more efficient and does
this fit with wiser you know I think
people have a tendency to think that as
they're gonna get old they're gonna grow
wise and I think some people grow wise
with age but not everyone
I think if some people never have
humility they will never grow wise a
humility is one of the preconditions for
and that what happens as many people
they get humbled along the way to age
and there's the opportunities for wisdom
occur there but I think there's a kind
of non humility or a kind of error
against that's deep in the AI
orientation that potentially limits
people's ability to open the wisdom and
the number one for me is death
acceptance you know I mean I've done so
much stuff on death acceptance I was on
sabbatical last winter and I just
finished my most recent book and I'm
really excited it's gonna be coming out
next year oh yeah yeah it's called
nothing exists and it's undeath
acceptance but it's a source of absence
anon being a little bit Heidegger in
there but jean-paul Sartre a lot of
Douglas Hardy had listeners stuff I mean
I really like arty stuff yeah Shirin
Lynn Margulis enduring saying and doing
a lot of stuff on them but I mean I
think you know to me accepting death is
so is so important you know I saw a Joe
Rogan and he was talking with I think
Brian Greene again there's the physicist
it was a great great podcast but at one
point he asks Brian Greene asked Rogen
he says you know if they could do like
Kurzweil would like and do the neural
net download into an artificial machine
would you do it and Rogan says well hmm
no he says well if you would ask me ten
years ago I probably would have said yes
but now you know I've done too many like
serious psychedelics particularly DMT
and he goes I want to know what happens
when the lights go out you know and Part
B wanted to go very weird how you got
from the question of would you do the
neural net download to somehow you want
to know what happens when the light's
gone you know part of me wants to go
where's the death acceptance because I
think what happens you know and I think
there are people who undergo a serious
psychedelic experience and then they
experience ego death and then after
they've experienced a reality that's
beyond their ego it's easy to slide into
there must be life after death no that
was you alive em on a psychedelic
experience I think many people who have
serious legged Elek experiences if
people it lends them the ability to grow
comfortable with death
yeah so it's like rogue in its unless
saying he misidentified his own
experience but it's almost like instead
of saying I think the psychedelics have
so tamed my fear of death that I'm
willing to just see what happens I'm not
scared of it anymore but instead it was
almost like he was a imagine you were
trying to she was trying to see you
Brian
Brian Greene was gonna bite on the mind
our brains be antenna I and you know it
was kind of a strange moment and I'm I
don't know but I'm banking everything
that I don't think anyone's ever gonna
find out what happens after your dad I
think when you're dead you can that's
the deal that's pessimism or nil ISM
it's beautiful this is how you know you
are the opening of the world you're the
way the world's worldly you know people
are reciting they don't know who they
really are
they've covered over that and now
they're worried about the continuance of
this little tiny sack of skin they take
of themselves to believe how tragic yeah
it's just impoverished so so what was it
like what was it what was it like the
experience of her how long have you been
writing this book oh man this probably
took you know notes of well over a
decade but I wrote it over the
sabbatical so I started writing last
January and I wrote most of it over the
semester then through the summer and I
had the chance to you know I'll do some
tightening up of it and yeah I'm really
excited about it it's gonna be roughly
it'll be a trilogy so it'll fit together
with my stuff and authenticity and the
sources of significance the most three
will be you know this will be my seventh
book those three kind of hang together
most sort of existentialist sort of
pieces I could see that I could and I I
think you know I did do a good number of
videos on nothing that were you know all
my videos they're unscripted they're
off-the-cuff it's me in the morning I'm
there in a mood I'm like I'm gonna talk
about this whatever so they're really
wrong there they're all scripted but I
did do a lot of videos on nothing and it
was fun for me to then take the time to
really carefully lay out my arguments on
paper instead of this on the copier on
the video but I mean
she's lay the stuff out I feel very very
confident anybody wants to go under
nothing this stuff I'm ready
[Music]
he was gonna try to tell me that nothing
doesn't exist I'm going to accuse them
immediately of not having read the book
yes anyone's gonna read it and first
they're gonna go I don't buy it they're
gonna get about 50 pages in and go boy
this is tougher than I thought a hundred
pages in they're gonna go oh my word how
could I have thought otherwise
and by the end they're going uncle uncle
you're right I give up there's no way
out there's you know there's no way out
of the nothing to stuff I think it's
really Heidegger you know I think like
for Heidegger nothingness is on par with
B it's not a being he's interested in
the being of beings the being of beings
has to entertain the nothing present
when he says them nothingness nuts
especially when you go to his essay on
what is metaphysics I mean here's a I
have all kinds of examples I mean the
book is just filled with examples to
demonstrate it but take something like
there's no Julius Caesar he is a
historical figure but that means he had
been alive but he no longer is this his
non being is part of how he is right now
that's what he has he had been you know
think of insurance I mean insurance
basically works from the insurance
providers having you pay for what might
happen but largely they make their money
by it not happening right an ante if
nante is an object who's here we can see
it but the world intuitive fits is gone
now the word the human one's ancestor
worship makes perfect sense being
cultures everywhere because the human
world is a world of absent presences
it's a world where we could talk about
Julius Caesar we could talk about you
know my dog who died and you know she's
not here anymore
but she's in pictures she's in video I
just I can talk about her
yeah she's language is the house of
being because language opens us up to
all of those things that can only be
through their non-being
that is absent presences yes stirring
itself yeah it kind of exfoli think the
more that somebody really is gonna be
honest with themselves there's no way
out of the non-being problem right we've
inherited a Western tradition which
tried to make it seem and it partly was
a religious tradition about sort of this
being excluding non-being
but the world that we have is a temporal
world it's a world that was and will be
and the wasn't it will be are not that's
their being I say it's not the present
yeah but it is the past I'm what it is
I'm working through I'm working through
I said nishitani z-- religion and
nothingness
have you okay yeah that's uh it he
basically kind of runs he kind of stands
you could say in something like
something like what the what what the
Japanese referred to as a like a like
nothingness right or emptiness in this
in this deep sense and then runs western
metaphysics through it from that and
like views it from that perspective it's
just it turns everything on its head in
this very foreign but rich kind of way
the so quick for you right so so what
you think what you're saying right is
you're basically saying like no look it
to say that like you can't escape the
nothing problem right is basically
saying that you can't escape your being
and that is really tied to the
connection between nothingness and our
death I guess what I would say okay well
that's right that's right and I would
come at it more directly and the high
daguerreian move here which would be in
order to get at being you're gonna have
to deal with time and thought and time
and thought are not a thing they're not
a thing
mine is a kind of relation of past
present and future
but thought is that peculiar kind of
time which inherently deals with
non-being yeah okay the hot is that kind
of time
that inherently deals with not being a
thought that dealt only in actualities
will be thought at all and in the same
way that thought in time largely resists
scientific compositional analysis a kind
of reductive science and it's gonna have
that you guys have a much more
complicated science in order to deal
with problems of time and thought you
know I think Terence deacons book
incomplete nature is a great exemplar of
some of this but I think at that point
if people are going to admit that time
is very nebulous and thought is very
nebulous well then of course you're
gonna get the problem that nothing is
going to be is equally nebulous as far
as time if I say to you I'm real people
go sure if I go is thought real they go
sure if I say there's nothing real to go
what have you gone crazy you want to go
look there's no way to have time without
man being yeah yeah yeah you know here's
one again one of the examples in the
book right so I'm there and I look and I
see a wine glass on the table and I see
a dog come over and the dog's tail is
wagging back and forth around the glass
now I can think about the possibility of
that glass being spilled so I move it
away on another shelf the non spilling
never occurs empirically so thoughts
ability to make the world orderly as it
is it covers over itself that is the
world is the orderly place that it is
because people avoid going where they
know they're not welcome this is the
problem with the pandemic that's
happening right now there are many
people going
if we act right now people are going to
think we overreacted because they're
gonna prevent the spread from happening
and then once it's prevented those who
thought they were overreacting about
look you overreacted it didn't spread we
know they're overreacting
wasn't an overreaction that's what made
it not happen exactly yeah it's it's
interesting I also I think bomb talks
about this right where he really does a
really good job of just dislodging
thought from kind of internal
representations and to imaging that
looky we don't we make this weird
division between objects and thinking
but
like you know that pillow right that
pillow is accommodating a whole future
of concerns that aren't here that isn't
that isn't an object out in the world
over there that is thinking like
everything of moved if David Bohm I
would that's he's great on all of this
and I'm thought as a process
I'm thought being more like the weather
and something below direct conscious
control at least more than we think so I
mean we can try to consciously control
our thought and we kind of consciously
control our breathing but as soon as we
forget to do it it just picks up on its
own autonomous chord whether we want it
to or not you know you can have thoughts
that you know we wouldn't ever want to
claim responsibility for because they
just spontaneously crop up there and
again you see the Eagle function which
sort of identifying and dis identifying
with the thoughts that crop up right
into it so kind of back to death right
right so when you mean
making peace with death right is part
like I basically hear that is like the
most important thing yes that's wisdom
yeah wisdom begins with death acceptance
right it's a real humility about who you
are right so when I accept death I think
I don't think what you're I don't think
what you're saying is like I accept
there's a line out there in the future
that I'm gonna cross right and when I
have a frosted you're not talking about
the event of deceasing no no I'm not
what I'm talking about a way of living
and it's it has to do with realizing
that one's on loan to oneself yeah
realizing that one's partly other people
they partly vegetative that were partly
dreamless sleep errs that the opinion
that we have of ourselves in conscious
awaking life is is illusory and then I
think people think there's this soul
substance that is going to go on after
their death post-mortem and then that
shapes how they live their lives they
think that in some way if they commit
horrible evils they're the only one
who's going to be punished in the
afterlife or somewhere they know their
horrors our horror shows on all of us
and we have to suffer from those things
and to realize that we're all in this
together
and his beautiful book by Alfonso Ling
is called the community of those who
have nothing in common
look there's one community it's not age
it's not nationality it's not even being
human is that we're all dying and we're
dying together either you accept that
we're all dying or you want to live in
illusion people don't believe in chosen
people but they want to believe in
something like a salvation for them
rather than seeing it as the struggle
for justice in this world yeah I think
the people they don't really you know if
there isn't gonna be real justice in
this world there isn't gonna be justice
yeah yeah to imagine that you know Skyy
daddy is gonna make amends for all of it
right and it's gonna assure that justice
are protected so many people
psychologically they know that this
world is unjust there are so much
hardship so much luck to the draw and it
is horrifying how much some people are
born not only biologically with
advantages but socio historically wealth
all kinds of
other people biologically born with a
disadvantaged body a severely maybe
disabled body and also in social
political and I think once we accept
that and get real about it become adults
about it we got to do the best we can
about trying to alleviate all of these
world problems and not wait for some
other factor to come and do it by either
a miracle or by afterlife whatever that
is so sort of everything's gonna be fine
because no matter how bad it was
God's gonna make sure they have an
easier time in heaven or something yeah
weird story like that yeah that's that
sense of so there's a sense of so if I'm
cuz this is this is a I'm son some love
what we're talking about is closer to us
than ourselves right it's like on one
level what you're talking about is the
most the ontologically grounding
groundless ground of like before even
our inauthenticity is about death point
to this nature of our own death right
it's like you can't quite get out of it
but in that sense it's so difficult to
see right when you say death so if I'm
in death acceptance right and I'm living
in death acceptance
what is one of the ways that I would
know I think when you look at another's
face and you see the others face as the
only possible God you could ever repay
you're in the right domain I think if
people say well you know life is a gift
in repayable and I'm gonna try to give
it back to God
I think there's any way to repay God the
only way that to repay it is to love
your fellow human being you the earth to
take care of you know it could be you
know that our concern about animals I
mean I think there's a whole bunch of
horizons but it's to realize the the
eternality of the now that's the
divinity in the details it's not
something elsewhere it's about creating
great art it's about having wonderful
conversations it's about you know
spending your time as if it were your
life and
to have really high quality interactions
you know it's it's appreciating the
fleetingness of all of us yes any it
this is what's really interesting this
is kind of this this Anto trans
emanation thing that goes not going on
I'm getting the sense of like in the in
that the immersion in the immersing and
say to the in the face of the other and
like seeing the other as the one the
last person I'll ever see right on some
level I'm that's filled with finitude
but at the same time there is a cut
there's a it's interesting it's like
there's a there's a there's a going deep
but also transcending at the same time
like both of those are happening at the
same time it's really a rich I mean I
guess I see you know I think Douglas
Hardy and stuff like having no head is
the most perfect complement to both
Sartre z-- ontology and to heidegger's
you know work on design you know it's if
instead of seeing myself as a sack of
skin who just represents the world and
the world is this object independent of
me instead if I see myself as I
experience myself that is as the
Headless opening of the world that is
the world makes room for itself by limb
endless bodies the world is world in
itself through my my body which
naturally banishes for the sake of the
horizons you know I did this video a
while back called you are the sunset and
I have a little bit of that in the in
the book you know it's the Sun is always
setting and rising simultaneously the
planets just rotating but because of our
finitude because we have bodies because
we can turn west the sunset appears as a
phenomena but the sunset isn't a
phenomena independent of observers of
the world's reality shows itself only
with the help of bodies so the greatest
riches that you are are things that
can't be possessed one in the world ways
the world shows itself is with the help
of bodies I mean I just really like that
I like the kinesthetic swish I get with
that like because it's it's it dislodges
the
kind of the Cartesian you know subject
and it's very I think that's
phenomenologically like really accurate
right you ever give her done the two-way
looking exercise of Harding my answer
you so like when you look around and
look at everyone else everyone else they
look like a figure against the graph and
they have a whole body head to toe but
you look at your own body like you can
see like your limbs and going down but
maybe she's a little dot in your nose
but your your necklace right so he says
to do this what you do is you take your
hand out in front of you and you take an
index finger and you try to point to
where you think your face should be now
using your finger as the new basis try
to see what your fingers pointing to if
you do it see there's it literally shows
that nothing but that's the nothing that
makes room for everything it's the
original world room the world womb is
the emptiness that's pouring in through
your head lessness
and he recommends this to wait to learn
to do the two-way looking so in one
sense once you learn to see the
nothingness that you are that is the
nothingness that makes room for
everything then you do the two-way
looking you learn to look out at the
world in terms of its particulars will
also seem complemented by the absolute
emptiness and what you find is that
there's a total stillness like try the
experiment once once you really learn
how to see that nothing is walk through
space and see what happens or like have
someone else drive and sit in the car
when you're in the car you don't move
the stillness never moves its unmoving
it's the landscape changes yeah even as
you're walking everything around it the
headless list that you are is the
absolute stillness it's yeah it's that
which there is no richer and that's what
every one of us each of us is yeah each
of it doesn't you know your capacity for
world your what you know when you were a
baby you were infinite you were at large
you just worry your world and then
slowly you gave we all gave up on that
by some socially agreed-upon
what we can see in the mirror and we've
learned to think about ourselves and
what we do is we covered it over in one
erection and not spend it back the other
way other people like like this I'm
looking at you right now and I say oh
look I can see your face you have a head
that's on top of your body then I go you
know what I must be just like that where
I should say hey I wonder if your
headless like I am we dissolve it in one
direction not the other yeah yeah so
interesting and then thinking about like
before Mears ray became a thing
god that's such a weird because your
oral society before the mirror other
people decorate your face they decorate
your own face yeah faces for other
people you'll never know if you have a
beautiful or ugly face because it
depends upon who's looking see this is
part of the dynamic I think you were
going to be honest with ourselves we're
not in full possession of ourselves
we're a social historical clearing of
world that's partly constituted by
others like I could think of it
something as intimate is my own name I
didn't name myself other people gave me
that name by somehow growing up always
knowing my name so others so enter the
recess of consciousness and build it
from the inside out
interesting yeah and even like even then
even that would grants my how I stand
out my first name right is given to me
by someone else right where my last name
connects me with the rest of everything
this kind of standing out yeah which is
such an odd thing you know I think how
does the death relate to the time and
thought you know I think one way to say
it is we're walking straws as we're
straws who walk we have a hole on one
end a hole on the other and life pours
through us
we're not objects we're straws or
alimentary canal x' and the river of
life is flowing through us I mean I
think you're shedding skin on the
outside and all the way on the inside as
well it's like a straw that sheds both
its inner and outer layers as it moves
well there's a hole cut you know it's
funny I I'm really getting this sense
it's interesting as I'm walking as I'm
I'm walking into on one will about what
you're talking about is not you're not
talking about some new I yeah this is
actually phenomenologically more sound
than the absolute body by drew leader is
one of the best books on this the a
fashion body body
well that that kind of I did I have
noticed that when I meditate that
there's a
that especially sound man sound is
something like the how when you like
when you make room for sound like stop
it that sound is a whole other thing
this is one of the things I this is one
of the things that that that's
interesting that we're in a digital
culture I think a big part of it is
because we've become so visual oriented
right that it's hard to imagine and I
think you were the guy that got me into
all Walter Ong man that's talk about
like talk about like get long long is he
similar a hugger for me in that way
where you you're reading it and all of a
sudden the cube turns where to grok to
grok what a moment was like in oral but
like pre pre literate culture and now
many people would really benefit from
looking at his chapter called writing
restructures consciousness from the
orality and literacy book i mean he's
got a lot of books and a lot a lot of
stuff but that thing that chapter is
quite a respite through the forehead
women who's never really thought about
what literacy is and I was affected
consciousness this way brilliant it's
amazing it's amazing it's kind of like I
mean even just the sense of just just
the sense that I can abstract out a
sense of an autobiographical self
independent like it I don't even know if
that was possible until there was
literacy you know hey well we definitely
wouldn't have had the
we definitely wouldn't have had the
capacity to tolerate the novelty right
because so much was embedded into into
these rhythms and stuff like that right
I think the narrative dynamics I think
some of that is Eric a blocks the mute
Eric a blocks book the muse lends to
write is a really good book preface to
Plato is another really great work right
so you know I think that one of the
things I mean I mean we can talk for a
long time but what like one of the
things I was gonna ask you about was you
know did so so you see this kind of I
will call it like this kind of techno
framing
trained right just cruising by so much
to the point where like I've found out
not that long ago that there that the
current generation for example doesn't
it it doesn't really have a notion of
character for example prey of this kind
of sense of going through something
difficult right and I see this a lot in
this is actually kind of how I think
during this time why there's such a
thing called circling that I do I
I've learned it's as much point to the
time that we're in as it does to the
practice that I found right in that
there are so many different ways and
this is one of things I wanted to ask
you about specifically which is you know
I think before I think the moment was
actually the answering machine right
before the answering machine
i as far as I can tell and I think the
printing press and reading and
newspapers and and all that is is a
different it's a different thing but if
I wanted to have a neck like an invert
like an informational exchange I always
would at least it would have had to cold
you right before the answering machine
like and in that in in that that kind of
facing each other and talking and
confronting other innocent all the
ambiguity and the risk that comes with
that right it's inherently uncomfortable
right but life was such a way that in
order to do that I had to go through or
that relational events with people he
was just embedded in everything that we
did and then the answering machine I
think was the beginning of it and then
email and texting and all of a sudden
you introduced this division right where
rather than
having to call you up and go through the
this this coordinated participatory
thing which in some level is what what
shaped myself understanding those
interactions right are so crucial now
there's all these divisions where people
actually don't don't have to go through
that coordinated activity and so there's
just this instant exchange to where
events our in this generation events are
textual exchanges people like kids get
together and they like they'll text each
other or sometimes on the text and
that's what's real right and the
interactions Audion interactions and so
there's this kind of self concealing
sense about it and I'm just curious what
what is that what is what's what what's
what's it doing that for that the what
yeah what's your sense of that like
there's a lot of things going on there
you know it's Alfred should has a
concept called growing older together
you know and he was one of the early
phenomenologist early in phenomenologist
he became instrumental to the social
constructionist movement but you know
this notion of growing older together he
would say that there's a privileged kind
of communication it's where people's
co-share presence and they're able to
grow older together and what you've
identified as a lot of asynchronous
modes of communication where somebody is
at one place in one time and somebody
else at another place and maybe at
another time even and that's the answer
displaces that capacity rolled together
and I think that's that's one of the
dynamics that's maybe there and that it
accelerates a forms of narcissistic
and/or like individuated one side
interaction rather than real dialogic
interactive kind of sensibilities it
also even feeds into I think senses of
vulnerability management you know I
think people are they're caught with you
know without the practice and exercise
of spontaneous Interac
and they can feel you know daunting to
have to posse up resources right there
on the fly when they get to you know
pause and think about what they're going
to say if they're very used to texting I
think the thing that I would really want
to force there is it's it's changing the
way that we think about what
relationships are so just as an example
I think some young people are they're
struggling with relationships because
they think of relationships is this kind
of ongoing act of exchanging information
where's my wife and I we can just sit
there quietly you know watching the
sunset doing really nothing just kind of
just enjoying each other's company and
that is the relationship and that's part
of its dynamic where's if all of your
exchanges are back-and-forth with
texting you start to think that's what a
relationship is then you start to be
interaction phobic because you don't
know what to say you you're worried
about or even have material and so they
start to think about the relationship as
this this little tiny act of exchanging
information but it's this whole huge
dynamic and so they're I think they're
stressed out about relationships because
they don't know how to do them yeah yeah
totally in that and here's the thing
that's interesting to me is that ability
to do relationships right Tuco inhabits
right in silence right that kind of
dwelling dwelling together and being
dwelling and another and another and
dwelling you and then not then we and
dwell us that kind of deep participatory
sense of things just kind of to take it
at that level and introduce a division
where that becomes an option whereas
before because I think it's this isn't
somebody came into one of my courses and
he in fact I think he's from Michigan um
he his kids is actually his wife said
you know what the the Amazon rang the
doorbell the other day and yeah I think
has you know a 12 or 11 year old or
something
and the kid was so freaked out he
wouldn't answer the door yeah it's
interesting in in what what the husband
said I thought was really stood ease
like he said you know look it's always
been tariff I'd like to confront another
person is a whole badass name
right like they don't even know that
there's snakes that you're gonna have to
encounter in that right so it's like
it's it's it's wise to be terrified for
danger right no I think that's right but
I think you know other dynamics that are
filtering into this though is that they
have by the time they're 15 or 16 they
have consumed in highly condensed form
total relationships coming together into
song I mean they can soon on the media
these super lis highly distilled
representations of relationships where
they again goes from the person being
born to having children and all these
complex relationships and it all goes
down about a two-hour thing and they
consume so many thousands of hours of
that and now they have expectations
about the relationships you know that
they imagine that they're supposed to
unfold like the happily ever after
stories or the the kind of complexity
and then even like you leave they go on
TV they're gonna watch like some sitcom
they're gonna watch a show like that 70s
show or whatever they're gonna watch
right Big Bang Theory where they're
watching and they forget that those
people are saying scripted lines and
then they look at their own life and
they're like well I'm not witty and
funny like most people are and it's like
no most people aren't that funny and
aren't that witty these are people who
are getting scripted lines is took a
whole team to come up with this stuff
that these are actors who are saying and
I so I think a lot of people have very
unrealistic expectations about how to be
a relationship partner how to how to
think all this kind of stuff I mean you
have to begin with some humble
beginnings and you work your way up man
impatience times gonna pass right right
and your boy Dan you don't practice
you're never gonna get good at it
totally and went and one of the things
that I'm kind of that's kind of eerie
right and like kind of see seeing the
uncanny nosov it is things of it is is
that so
what like for example I don't have to go
I can just order my food on Amazon I
could literally like that I think this
is the first time in history where all
you need is basically a computer and
internet connection and maybe an
apartment and you could you could like
start a company you could become like
epically famous right you can be on
videos you could be and never have to
ever come in contact with another person
right this uh there's just something
about like I kind of when I kind of step
back from that and I just kind of sense
the whole of it like what is that sense
I mean is it is it have to do with this
kind of bubbles bubble that happened
with with literacy training one way to
come in it would be something like this
that and I should probably go soon maybe
will come because this is gonna be like
an endless conversation but I think it
would be just a Pandora's box here but I
mean I think it's some way you know the
human being is that organism that part
of nature which specialized in math
specialization that was our specialty
that is we don't have any particular
ecological niche that were embedded in
we have wide dietary practices you ask
what is the mating ritual of the human
well it depends upon what culture you go
to you can't just do again this is huge
wide and openness and in some way you
might say that you know it's almost as
if nature experimented with opening up
ranges of the experience of freedom and
agency at a certain place in you know
like and we're we're that and in some
way you can see it that this organism is
not going to stop thrashing around until
it figures out a way to hide or you get
out of the agency that's been sentenced
to and it wants to create a social
determinism to make up for the loss of
the biological determinism and most
other organism sort of like locked into
so that they don't have to experience
conscience and choice and the agony of
you know decision making but there is
that other extreme of those capacitated
agencies through technologies they
afford greater
trol at the push of a button and so you
can sort of see in some way this this
thrashing about in the free space and
nature is trying to maximize its power
and it's reaching its range and
insufficiency while simultaneously
trying to get out of it and you can sort
of imagine a kind of determinism of an
agency wedding together in the strangest
of ways man totally totally
I really like the way that you put that
I'm gonna be I'm gonna be thinking about
that those are all the kind of thought
these open horizons have just been kind
of wiggling through as I walk around and
just kind of well guy I mean I really
appreciate you you know contacted me and
yeah let me know if you want to talk
again sometime I'll send you some links
are just some of the people I've been
like that we've we've mentioned in which
there was a book that you had mentioned
something about what was it the the bots
it's the body one but you know
absolutely body by drew leader yeah he's
a he's a medical doctor and a
phenomenologist it's very well-written
and really captures the difference
between the body as cadaver or the body
of another versus one his body that one
is it's lived the lived body is design
the live body is the openness of being
there and being here simultaneously yes
okay great it's been great having you're
here there yeah it's really been fun
thank you so much yeah I'll be in
contact okay you take care